Daniel Duclos-Cavalcanti

Computer Engineer

516-912-7975 | New York, NY | U.S. Citizen | $\underline{\text{me@duclos.dev}}$ | $\underline{\text{www.duclos.dev}}$ | $\underline{\text{linkedin}}$ | $\underline{\text{github}}$

Summary

Creative thinker and problem-solver with a masters and bachelors in computer engineering from Germany. Today, I am in New York, collaborating on research with Dr.Sivaraman (NYU) on distributed low-latency networking on the cloud.

Technical Skills

Languages: C++, Python, Golang, Rust, C, Bash, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Lua, VHDL

Cloud Services: Google Cloud Platform (GCP), Amazon EC2 (AWS), Terraform, Packer, Vagrant Tools: Linux, Unix Shell, Git, Github CI/CD, Jenkins, CMake, GNU Make, Bazel, Vim, VSCode

Technologies: Docker, ZeroMQ, DPDK, MPI, FreeRTOS, FPGA, IoT, TensorFlow, Scipy, NumPy, Pandas, OpenMP

Verbal/Written: German – Fluent, Portuguese – Fluent

Experience

Research Assistant

Jul 2022 - Oct 2022

TU Munich

- Munich, Germany • Worked on <u>TensorDSE</u>, a Design-Space Exploration framework to guide machine learning model deployments.
- Evaluated the performance of various ML models across GPUs, CPUs and TPUs with TensorFlow Lite.
- Generated cost analysis reports for Google's Coral Edge TPU via USB traffic analysis (PyShark) during inference.
- TensorDSE used reports to distribute a model's inference/deployment optimally onto available hardware devices.

Embedded Software Engineer – Internship

Aug 2021 – Jan 2022

Ottobrunn. Germany

- Added unit-tests (GTest) and code coverage (lcov) to safety critical features of their motor's embedded controller.
- Developed tooling for state simulations of their electric motor via Linux's virtual CAN interface and mock APIs.
- Extended their firmware update system used by 20+ clients, consisting of partial updates via CAN bus.
- Automated build and testing workflows via Jenkinsfiles, Makefiles and CMake for a team of over 10 engineers.

Projects

Cloud-TreeBuilder | GCP, Terraform, Python, C++, Distributed Systems, Heuristic

Mar 2024 - Present

- Launches and selects K out of N VMs in a cluster to create an optimal multicast tree of depth D and fan-out F.
- Uses UDP probe jobs to examine VMs network performance, selecting instances for a tree layer by layer.
- Uses terraform to manage cloud state, ZMQ for node communication and Protobufs for data serialization.

Hamming Code Error Detection | C, VHDL, FPGA, SoC

2022 - 2023

- Error detection/correction algorithm for packet transmission on Microsemi's SF2 FPGA/SoC.
- Microprocessor offloads error-injected data onto the FPGA fabric for correction via an APB3 Bus Matrix.

Open-MPI Value Iteration | C++. Parallel-Computing. MPI. HPC

- An HPC prototype that solves a stochastic navigation problem through Asynchronous Value Iteration (AVI).
- Used different OpenMPI techniques to iteratively distribute workload across an HPC cluster and gather results.

Publications

Design and Implementation of A Scalable Financial Exchange in the Cloud | (Paper)

- Novel Cloud financial exchange achieving low latency of <= 250 μs, with a difference < 1 μs for 1K receivers.
- Used kernel-bypass techniques (DPDK) to scale and achieve ~\% lower latency than AWS's multicast service.

EDUCATION

New York University: Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences

Computer Science - Visiting Non-Degree Graduate Student

Sept 2023 – May 2024

GPA 4.0

- Co-Authored Publication: Design and Implementation of A Scalable Financial Exchange in the Cloud
- Related Coursework: Operating Systems, Technologies in Finance

Technical University of Munich

Oct 2020 - Oct 2024

M.Sc. Electrical and Computer Engineering Munich, Germany

- M.Sc. Thesis: VM Selection Heuristic for Multicast Overlay Trees in the Cloud
- Related Coursework: Machine Learning Methods, Computer Networks, High Performance Computing Lab Embedded Design for Machine Learning, Embedded Systems Programming Lab, Secure SoC for IoT

Technical University of Munich

Oct 2016 - Sept 2020

B.Sc. Electrical and Computer Engineering

Munich, Germany